<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A little eye-salve for the kingdome and armie, that they may see. VVherein is cleerly represented what the supreme power of the kingdome is, and how it may be knowne. / By a true friend and lover of those powers and magistrates that be of God.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88369</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862916</idno>
  <idno type="VID">115096</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240950555</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2548</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E417_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202721</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862916</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99862916e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88369)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115096)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 66:E417[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A little eye-salve for the kingdome and armie, that they may see. VVherein is cleerly represented what the supreme power of the kingdome is, and how it may be knowne. / By a true friend and lover of those powers and magistrates that be of God.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeere 1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing; publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 27 1647".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Church and state --  England --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Pas </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115096:1"/>
            <head>A little Eye-Salve for the Kingdome and Armie, that they may see. VVherein is cleerly represented what the Supreme Power of the Kingdome is, and how it may be knowne. <hi>By a true Friend and Lover of those Powers and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates that be of God.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Lord who is wonderfull in councell and excellent in working, who had according to his determinate will, as it were, withdrawne himselfe from the world, in the fore-going ages, hath now latey appeared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in this Kingdome in some wonderfull workes of his, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as it appears, about some notable designe for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdome of his deare Son.</p>
            <p>We who have lived in any light of God, are not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant how that in this last age the supreme Magistrates of the Kingdome, had turned aside from the power of God, as well as from the way of God, and went about to strengthen themselves in their owne wayes, and to accomplish their owne designes by a multitude of evill doers, whom they every where encouraged, maintained, and preferred, that they might be serviceable to themselves in whatever their hearts should desire; and in this wicked way of their owne choosing, God in his secret and just judgement suffered them to prosper, till they had even almost oppressed all common justice, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and honesty in the State, and all spirituall worship and power of godlines in the Church. And then it became the fulnesse of time, for God to arise himselfe, and to stretch forth his owne arme, and for his own names sake to vindicate his own power in the State, and Christs in the Church: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord sounds an Alarum and gathers together a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115096:2"/> in the Kingdome, (not the first power, which was of mans choosing rather then Gods, and whom he cast off, as he cast off <hi>Saul;</hi> but the second power which was of his owne chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing and annointing, and whom he was with, as he was with <hi>David</hi>) and by this second power he breakes the Shield, the Sword and the Battell, he makes the Kings and Princes of the Army to fly, while the poore Countrey-people divide the spoile; and by this he utterly subdues the enemy in all his power of war. But this puts not an end to our evils, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces us unto our former peace, as we were in good hope; but through the weake and wicked administrations of some, and the just judgement of God over all, the whole Kingdom is become one generall heap of confusion and disquiet, and no man now knowes which are those hills to which he should turne his eyes, or which are those mountaines from whence he should expect help, and the great question of all men at this time is, <hi>where now lies the supreme power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this matter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> crave leave of all my deare Countrimen, to speak freely my own apprehensions, not for the prejudice of any one man, much lesse of a whole Common-wealth, but for the profit and satisfaction of all.</p>
            <p>The supreme power then in the Kingdome, is the <hi>power of God</hi> where ever it is to be found, and he cannot avoid the just censure of Atheisme who will deny, that <hi>the power of God is the supreme power,</hi> and that this supreme power of God ought to reigne in the world: for that remaines an unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable truth, that it is <hi>the most high God that reignes in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of men;</hi> it is not men themselves that are to reigne in those Kingdomes they call their owne, nor the Devill that is to reigne by and through men, but it is the most high God that is to reigne, and the whole power of Government, both of this and all other Nations, is to be the <hi>power of God.</hi> Now the power of God reignes in the Kingdomes of men, sometimes under one forme, and sometimes under another; sometimes under <hi>Monarchy▪</hi> sometimes under <hi>Aristocracy,</hi> sometimes under <hi>Democracy,</hi> &amp;c. and it is no matter what the outward forme of Government be, so the power of God be <hi>underneath is:</hi> For it is not any <hi>forme of Government,</hi> that we are to stand by, and submit to, but the <hi>power of God</hi> in it;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115096:2"/> but when the power of God leaves any forme of Government, we are not to stand by that forme, when it is destitute of the power of God, but we are to go along with the power of God, where ever that goes, and where that remaines we are to joyn, and there we are to submit our selves. This may be thus illustrated: The presence of God is, that which the Church is to joyne to, where ever it is to be found; now in the dayes of the Old Testament the presence of God for Worship was promised to the <hi>Temple, here will I dwell sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h God,</hi> and therefore all the faithfull worshipped towards the Temple at Jerusalem, not for the Temples sake, but for Gods Presence sake which dwelt in the Temple: But now when Christ comes, the Presence of God leaves the Temple, to which it was annexed onely by a word, and dwells bodily in Christ: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the faithfull quite leaving the Temple, as the presence of God left it, now come to Christ, in whom the fulnesse of the Godhead dwells bodily, and the Temple is nothing at all to them; but the Jewes staying by the Temple when the presence of God had left it, became a reproach, curse, desolation and astonishment. So in like manner in point of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, we may stay by any forme whilst the power of God is in it, but to stay by the forme, when the power of God is withdrawne, is to make our dwelling place with cruelty, tyranny, injustice, oppression and destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Now the common people of the Kingdome, they onely regard the outward forme of Government, but the wiser people of the Nation they most minde the power of God in the forme: The ignorance of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is the cause why they cry out so vehemently, Oh the King, the King, the King! and they say, they will never be quiet till they have the King againe, though he have quite cast off the power of God, and hath acted plainely and manifestly by a power as contrary to Gods, as darknesse is to light, and through that wicked power hath wasted Cities and Counties, and layed Townes and houses desolate, and slaine many thousands of men, women and children in England and Ireland, and hath drunk up our bloud as new wine, and fill'd both these Kingdomes with the sad outcries and lamentations of widdowes and orphans, and hath stuffed our borders full with mischiefs and miseries of all kinds; though I say, the <hi>King</hi> hath cast off Gods power, and to speake plainly, hath acted in the Devills, and though the power of God hath cast off him, and left him as a most remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable piece of weakenesse in the midst of the Nation, and as a man truly <hi>without strength,</hi> yet they, a foolish people and unwise, cry out for this King againe, wherein they clearly say, give us a Governour that hath none
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115096:3"/> of the power of God at all with him, but who is acted by a contrary power, for the destruction of all the just waies of God among men. <hi>And truly, such a King may well serve such a people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But those that are wise and rationall among us, they look above this <hi>regall forme:</hi> yea above all outward formes whatever, as well <hi>Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> as Regall, and that power which they will onely own and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, it is the power of God among what sort of people soever it is to be found; for they know, that this is the only <hi>power</hi> of God that can and will govern men in justice, judgement and righteousnesse: and if Government be committed to any sort of men that are without this power, the consequence will certainely be tyranny and oppression, as we have seen in these dayes of ours in more then many instances.</p>
            <p>To draw neare then to what I would say, if the King be destitute of the power of God, or the Parliament, or the like, they are no longer the supreme power, except we will resolvedly give up the Kingdomes of the world to the Devill, which not onely every Christian, but every man should contend against with all the power that God hath given him. But the power of God, though in a company of meane men, is absolutely the supreme power, to which all are to joyne themselves, and to which they are to submit: as we see in many instances of Scripture: for example, when the people of Israel were in Aegypt, they were all in an equall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of bondage, and no one man above another, and who would have thought to have seen a King or Ruler amongst them, and then the presence and power of God found out <hi>Moses,</hi> and abode with him, and he became the <hi>Supreme power,</hi> and though at first the Israelite refused to obey, saying, <hi>Who made thee a Ruler and Judge over us?</hi> Yet when it was more manifest that the power of God was with him, then not he onely, but all the <hi>people obey'd him,</hi> and after when <hi>Moses</hi> died, how came <hi>Joshua</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the rest, to be the <hi>supreme power,</hi> but because God said to him, <hi>I will be with thee as I have been with Moses.</hi> Further, when God <hi>departed</hi> from <hi>Saul,</hi> (a King of the peoples preremptory choosing) the <hi>Supreme power</hi> was no longer with him; but God choosing <hi>David</hi> a poore Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, the <hi>Supreme power,</hi> which is the power of God, became his, and the <hi>power of God</hi> with <hi>David,</hi> swallowed up by degrees the <hi>power of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> which was with <hi>Saul,</hi> and so the Kingdome came to be established in <hi>Davids</hi> hands. After this, when <hi>David</hi> died, how came <hi>Solomon</hi> a younger brother to be the <hi>supreme power</hi> rather then <hi>Adonijah</hi> the first borne, but because <hi>God appeared</hi> to <hi>Solomon</hi> and was with him, and was not with <hi>Adonijah,</hi> &amp;c. If any say, these were extraordinarie, and in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115096:3"/> first daies of the Church, I ansvver: No, it was Gods ordinarie way thus to deale, as you may see all along in the story of the Church, and God hath promised it shall be so also in the last daies of the Church, saying, <hi>Isa.</hi> 1. <hi>I will give them Judges as at the first, and Counsellours as at the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if any aske me, yea, but <hi>how shall wee know the power of God from other powers in the world,</hi> that we may come in unto that?</p>
            <p>I answer, the <hi>Apostle</hi> gives us an unerring Character of such pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>begin.</hi> where he saith, the <hi>Powers that be are ordained of God,</hi> and these Powers so ordained, <hi>do incourage and protect the good, and do ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify and revenge upon the evill,</hi> and in both these, they are the Ministers of God excercising his Power among men: &amp; <hi>Peter</hi> saith, <hi>the Governours to which we are to submit, are sent of God, for the punishment of evill doers, and for the praise of them that do well.</hi> And thus it is evident, what that power is that is of God, and unto which wee are to submit.</p>
            <p>Now if we look to the power that the <hi>King</hi> mannaged, it is notoriously knowne, that that power was a <hi>terror to the good, and a praise to the evill;</hi> that that <hi>power did punish the good, and reward the evill,</hi> and so was none of the power of God. How many good men in all parts of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome were vexed, oppressed, imprisoned, undone, banish'd, and driven in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other parts of the world for succour, for their lives and livelihoods? and how many evill men, Popish and Antichristian <hi>Prelates,</hi> luxurious and tyrannicall <hi>Lords,</hi> unjust and wicked <hi>Judges,</hi> together with a multitude of prophane and ungodly persons of all conditions, did the <hi>King</hi> counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, prefer, and put into places of trust and honour every where in the Kingdome? as if he had a <hi>project</hi> in his heart to strengthen himself against Jesus Christ, and totally to suppresse his <hi>Kingdome</hi> from having any place in his <hi>Dominions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when it was thus apparent, that the <hi>Kings</hi> power was not Gods power, but contrary to it, God (according to his usuall dealing) raises up <hi>another power</hi> in the Kingdome and breakes that in pieces: and then the <hi>power</hi> came in the hands of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> at first laid hold on Gods power, and were mighty through it as long as they did cleave unto it: but now they not learning righteousnesse by Gods judgements on the <hi>Kings</hi> power, did also turne aside from Gods power to their own, and they became as unjust, tyrannicall and oppressive as the former power, and much more, and so how busie, cunning and active became they to suppresse godly men every where, and to encourage, protect and prefer evill men that might be serviceable to their owne turne, after the example of the King, till at last God powred contempt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115096:4"/> upon them also, and raised up a sorry company of very servants and bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the <hi>City,</hi> the actors and executioners of their <hi>Masters counsells,</hi> to invade the power of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and to <hi>force</hi> them to make what Lawes they listed, which accordingly they did for feare of that rude multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: God hereby declaring his <hi>departure</hi> from that forme also, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering that the <hi>power left behind</hi> would now be content to be subject even to the lusts of servants, and so would never be able againe to stand out against the new temptations and courtings of the <hi>King,</hi> if he should returne againe.</p>
            <p>So that this present forme of the Parliament seemes to many men, <hi>as destitute of the power of God,</hi> as the former of the <hi>Kings;</hi> for I pray, what <hi>justice</hi> have they done, which concerned not themselves? What oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed ones have they releeved that were not related to themselves? What ends have they prosecuted, but their owne? And so under this <hi>present power</hi> of theirs doth not the Kingdome groane under a <hi>thousand</hi> oppressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for one heretofore? Are not all our burdens multiplied? And is not injustice, cruelty, oppression, and <hi>most Arbitrary</hi> power, spread as a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering over the whole Kingdome, by the hands of their <hi>Committees?</hi> and are not <hi>they themselves</hi> still preparing more snares, for the most precious of the people of God, and preparing more opposition and resistance to Christs spirituall worship? Do they not nourish <hi>Traytors to the Kingdome</hi> in their owne <hi>bosome,</hi> and hold them so fast in their <hi>armes,</hi> that no loud outcries for <hi>Justice</hi> can wring them forth? And now let the <hi>whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> judge, whether they be any longer the <hi>power of God,</hi> the Apostle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribes.</p>
            <p>But where then shall we find the power of God, if both <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> have declined from it, and are now found destitute of it?</p>
            <p>I answer, I see none of the <hi>power of God</hi> left in the Kingdome, if it be not to be found in the Army: for certainly <hi>the Power of God</hi> did first <hi>set</hi> them up, and since <hi>keep</hi> them up, and made its residence among them, and fought their battailes, and stormed their Cities and strong holds for them; and as <hi>the power of God</hi> hath produced <hi>them</hi> and their <hi>workes,</hi> so <hi>they</hi> againe have acted according to <hi>Gods power;</hi> and I have no where observed of late through the whole Kingdome, any power that hath incouraged and protected and countenanced the <hi>good,</hi> and cashiered, and punished and revenged upon the <hi>evill,</hi> as they have done; and therefore the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>powers</hi> remaining <hi>faint</hi> and <hi>sinnewlesse, this power</hi> only remaines hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>strong</hi> and <hi>mighty,</hi> and so is like to doe, as long as it remaines the <hi>power of God.</hi> But the <hi>Army</hi> of late also hath had its <hi>qualmes</hi> and <hi>Ague fits,</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115096:4"/> they have been <hi>departing from the power of God,</hi> divers of <hi>great place</hi> in it have become <hi>Faithlesse</hi> and <hi>Heartlesse,</hi> and durst not rest on that power alone, for the doing of the <hi>workes of God,</hi> and so have sought to strengthen themselves in vaine, by the two former empty formes of King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: yea they have suffered and constrain'd the <hi>power of God</hi> in and among them (which ought alwaies to be active and operative) to ly still for many moneths together; till the Axel-tree of the Kingdom is crackt quite asunder, and the very foundations of it are tottering, and confusion and ruine like a <hi>desperate sicknesse</hi> is spreading it selfe through all the members of it, and yet they sit still and do not helpe at all. And this is the great and <hi>crying sin</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> at this time; they say, <hi>they are the servants of the Parliament, and they must expect their commands.</hi> And are you yet no further? are you yet bewitched and benummed with those Syrens that are among you? can <hi>you, honest and valiant men,</hi> see the whole Kingdome fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming about your eares, and stand still till you have a Commission to goe quench it? can you heare the <hi>outcries</hi> of <hi>thousands</hi> and <hi>Millions</hi> from all parts of the Kingdome, crying out to you, as the man of <hi>Macedonia</hi> to <hi>Paul, come and helpe us, Oh helpe us, helpe us,</hi> from the bondage, oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, injustice, delayes, vexations, undoings and grindings to powder of the Ministers of Parliament, Sequestrators, Countrey-Committees, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Committees, and many such like instruments of woe, who are suck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the very <hi>bloud,</hi> and eating out the very <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>bowells</hi> of the Kingdome, and see and heare all this, and ly still at <hi>free quarters,</hi> and <hi>sleep</hi> on the best beds, and <hi>fare</hi> at the best tables, as if this nothing concerned you? know you not yet that <hi>Necessity</hi> is not to be tyed by any <hi>Lawes,</hi> nor to be limited by any forms? know you not that to <hi>relieve the oppressed,</hi> and to <hi>break in pieces the oppressors,</hi> and what ever else is <hi>materially</hi> good, is lawfull to be done in case of <hi>necessity.</hi> If a Troope of your horse march by the high way, and see rogues and robbers spoilng an <hi>honest</hi> man, will you passe by and refuse to helpe him, till your <hi>General</hi> give you a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission</hi> for that particular businesse? How then can you answer it to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> to suffer so many men, and their inheritances, to be oppressed and spoiled, to see <hi>Committee</hi>-men and <hi>Cavaliers</hi> tread up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the neeks of the <hi>free borne</hi> people of <hi>England</hi> and to make them bow downe, that they may goe over them, whilest you have power to helpe and succour them, but yet prolong still, and refuse to doe it, because the <hi>Parliament hath not commissioned you with any such kind of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er:</hi> And must the power of God in the Kingdome ask leave of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the world and of the Devill, to do justice among men? Must the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115096:5"/> power of God be still smothered under a thousand formes, and be kept out of sight, by the customes and traditions of men, that it may not act clearly and above all things among us? That which among many creatures would be a great evill would be a great good among you, to wit, to <hi>know your own power:</hi> that is, to know how the power of God in the world is power above all power, a free, absolute, universall power, not to be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited by any formes, persons, times or places, but is still to be uppermost in the world. And therfore know, that God hath raised you up for such a time as this is, and if you refuse to help this distressed Nation, whose throat is now become so hoarse with calling for help, that it cannot speak many words more, God will find deliverance for us some other wayes, but you, all of you, shall perish: and you that would not help the afflicted, shall be your selves afflicted, and none shall help you. Yea all the wrongs, oppressions, miseries, woes and evills of this whole Kingdome shall lie upon your heads, whom God had armed with power to remedie them, but you would not.</p>
            <p>And therfore bitter shall be the cup of those wise Officers of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who leaving the wisdome of God, have gone down to sense and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to ask counsell, and to politike men of carnall principles; for their wisdome is their snare, and they have deserted the way of faith. And the Lord be the strength of those men-children, who have appeared as the <hi>first fruits of the power of God</hi> in the lapsed state of the Army, whose faithfull and powerfull agitations I look upon as some first buddings of Christs Kingdome among us: and increased of God be their faith, who dare undertake, without any humane help, such a work, wherein they are like to find all the power, honour, riches, wisdome, learning, Gentry, Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Royalty of the Kingdome against them; and yet the power of God with them will carrie on his own work against all these, which shall all fall backward before it, as those Officers, who being armed with world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly power to apprehend Christ, fell down backward before Christ the power of God.</p>
            <p>And therefore let such godly men, as they have begun in faith, so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the same faith, and let all that see the presence and power of God with them, come in unto that power; for what is impossibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to our pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, is possible to his, <hi>who worketh all things after the counsell of his own will.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed in the Yeere 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>